A Guide to the Lemuel Durbin Williams Papers, 1842-1885 [bulk, 1853-1862]
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Lemuel Durbin Williams Papers, 1842-1885 [bulk, 1853-1862]
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
158
2 boxes (0.5 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the collector, Mr. Robert Strathy, 2006.
Biographical/Historical Information
Lemuel Durbin Williams (1831?-1865) was a member of the Washington Light Infantry militia for several years prior to the start of the Civil War. When the D.C. Militia Infantry was formed to defend Washington D.C. in the early days of the Civil War, he joined the Washington Light Infantry for a 3-month tour of duty on April 10, 1861 and initially served as a 1st Lieutenant. Upon the promotion of Captain Lemuel Towers a month later, Williams was promoted to Captain and took command of the company. He was mustered out on July 10, 1861. Influenced by his work with a volunteer militia and his service in the Civil War he published one military instruction manual early in 1861 and wrote two other related works that apparently were never published.
By profession Williams was a draughtsman. He worked for the United States Coast Survey and later for the Northwest Boundary Survey Office. Examples of maps that Williams worked on can be found online at the Library of Congress American Memory site. Information about additional maps can be found on the American Philosophical Society website. Professionally and for publication he used the names L.D. Williams and Lem D. Williams. His outside interests extended to submitting two designs for a Treasury note; he received the offered premium because significant amounts of his designs were incorporated into the final product.
Williams married Sarah M. O'Donnell in 1852. He died at age 34 on July 31, 1865 after a short illness. He was survived by his wife and six children.
Scope and Content
The collection is primarily focused on Williams' membership in the Washington Light Infantry, his published and unpublished works on proper performance of various military duties, and his work for the Coast Survey. The collection contains a work log from his days at the Coast Survey, correspondence received by Williams, and his published and unpublished works, including one which was written over part of a daily log from his service in the D.C. Militia Infantry.
Arrangement
The collection is organized thematically into the following categories: Biographical, U.S. Coast Survey, Washington Light Infantry, Works, Treasury Note Designs, Souvenir.
Index Terms
United States Coast Survey; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Washington Light Infantry; Williams, L.D.
Contents List
- Biographical. (Box-folder 158:1)
- U.S. Coast Survey - daily log, 1853-1857. (Box-folder 158:2)
- U.S. Coast Survey - correspondence with Jacob Monk, 1859-1862. (Box-folder 158:3)
- U.S. Coast Survey - notes. (Box-folder 158:4)
- Washington Light Infantry - membership records, 1842-1858. (Box-folder 158:5)
- Washington Light Infantry - correspondence, 1861-1864. (Box-folder 158:6)
- Washington Light Infantry - dance card, 1885. (Box-folder 158:7)
- Works - American Illustrated Military Textbook, 1861. (Box-folder 158:8)
- Works - Laws and Principles Governing in the Field, Camp and Garrison. (Box-folder 158:9)
- Works - Diary of Command and Notes on a new/revised Work. (Box-folder 158:10)
- Treasury Note Designs. (Box-folder 158:11)
- Souvenir ($50 Confederate bill). (Box-folder 158:12)
- Muster roll for Company A, Washington Light Infantry District, April 10, 1861. (Box-folder 158A:1)
- Flyer advertising The American Illustrated Military Text Book. (Box-folder 158A:2)